Guide to the Commencement Exercises Reference Collection, 1850-2023 UA.01.11.0041
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Commencement Exercises Reference collection
1850-2023
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Archives
UA.01.11.0041
6.75 Linear Feet
The Commencement Exercises Reference Collection contains commencement programs; addresses, speeches, and sermons; and associated material.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
This collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research.
Historical Note
On November 21, 1852 the State of North Carolina authorized Normal College, Duke's predecessor institution, "to grant such degrees and marks of honor as are given by colleges and universities generally." The institution first awarded A.B. degrees the following year, and thus 1853 is our "degree date." Two brothers, D. C. and Lemuel Johnson, were the recipients, and made up the first graduating class. The 2009 commencement was the one hundred and fifty seventh. The University began printing commencement numbers on the programs in 1932, when that year's was marked as the eightieth commencement. The count therefore was started with the 1853 ceremony. Union Institute and Normal College did celebrate commencement before 1853; however no degrees were awarded at those ceremonies.
Collection Overview
The collection contains programs, transcripts or copies of commencement and baccalaureate addresses, invitations, announcements, honorary degree citations, instructions to participants, news clippings, lists of speakers, Bibles, sample diplomas, and other materials pertaining to commencement ceremonies. From 1850 through 1927, one folder typically holds materials from several years' ceremonies, whereas in more recent years, one's year's ceremony may take more than one folder.
- Bibles (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1983- (Box 2)
- Memoranda and Notes, 1972- (Box 2)
- Speakers: Commencement, 1893-; Baccalaureate, 1892- (Box 2)
- Diplomas and diploma cases (samples), 1937 and 1980 (Box 2)
- Duplicates, 1900-1939 (Box 17)
- 1850-1909, 18 folders
  - Programs, clippings, letters and other (Box 3)
- 1910-1930, 8 folders
  - Programs (Box 4)
- 1931
  - Programs (Box 4)
  - Address: Pres. William Preston Few, The Unity of Architecture at Duke University and the Ideas that Underlie it (Box 4)
- 1932
  - Programs (Box 4)
  - Address: Pres. William Preston Few, The Discipline of Suffering (Box 4)
- 1933
  - Programs (Box 4)
- 1934
  - Programs (Box 4)
  - Address: Sir Wilfred Greenfell, The Way to Wisdom (Box 4)
- 1935-1937, 3 folders
  - Programs (Box 4)
- 1938
  - Programs (Box 4)
  - Sermon: Norman Vincent Peale, The Fate of Our Society (Box 4)
- 1939
  - Programs (Box 4)
  - Addresses: Pres. William Preston Few and James R. Awgell (Box 4)
  - Sermon: Bishop Garfield Bronley Oxnam (Box 4)
- 1940
  - Programs (Box 4)
  - Address: William Allan Neilson (Box 4)
- 1941-1945, 10 folders
  - Programs (Box 5)
- 1946
  - Programs and Programs for School of Nursing (Box 5)
- 1947-1948, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 5)
- 1949
  - Programs (Box 5)
  - Sermon: James T. Cleland (Box 5)
  - Address: Walter H. Judd, Which Direction Toward Peace (Box 5)
- 1950
  - Programs (Box 5)
  - Address: Charles Dollard (Box 5)
  - Sermon: Ralph W. Sockman, Make Up Your Mind (Box 5)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 5)
- 1951
  - Programs (Box 5)
  - Address: Robert Calkins, In Quest of the Great Age" (Box 5)
  - Address: Pres. A. Hollis Edens (Box 5)
  - Sermon: Paul E. Scherer, What Do You Make of Life? (Box 5)
- 1952
  - Programs (Box 5)
  - Address: Grayson Kirk (Box 5)
  - Sermon: Paul Hardin, A Plea for Vital Virtues (Box 5)
- 1953
  - Programs (Box 5)
  - Address: Harold Urey, The Intellectual Revolution (Box 5)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 5)
- 1954
  - Programs (Box 5)
  - Address: Reuben Gilbert Gustarson (Box 5)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 5)
- 1955
  - Programs (Box 5)
  - Address: Hodding Carter (Box 5)
- 1956
  - Programs (Box 5)
  - Sermon: Russell J. Humbert, Freedom-Some New Dimensions (Box 5)
- 1957
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 6)
- 1958
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Address: Charles S. Rhyne, Law as a Plan for Peace (Box 6)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 6)
- 1959
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Address: Ralph McGill (Box 6)
- 1960
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Address: David D. Henry, Concern for Consensus (Box 6)
  - Sermon: Goodrich White, The Ordered Life (Box 6)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 6)
- 1961
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Remarks: Pres. Deryl Hart (Box 6)
  - Sermon: Julian N. Hartt, The End in View (Box 6)
  - Address: William S. Middleton, Man's Fulfillment (Box 6)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 6)
- 1962
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Address: Dr. Gaylord P. Harnwell (Box 6)
- 1963
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Address: Merrimon Cununggim (Box 6)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 6)
- 1964
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Address: Calvin Bryce Hoover (Box 6)
  - Sermon: Pres. Douglas M. Knight (Box 6)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 6)
- 1965
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Address: Gordon Norton Ray (Box 6)
  - Sermon: Pres. Douglas M. Knight (Box 6)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 6)
- 1966
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Address: Charles Hard Townes (Box 6)
  - Sermon: Pres. Douglas M. Knight (Box 6)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 6)
- 1967
  - Programs (Box 6)
  - Address: Robert Stanley Rankin (Box 6)
  - Sermon: Pres. Douglas M. Knight (Box 6)
- 1968
  - Programs (Box 7)
  - Address: Dr. Barnes Woodhall, I Dissent (Box 7)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 7)
- 1969
  - Programs (Box 7)
  - Address: Angier Biddle Duke, Observations on Military Power and Foreign Policy (Box 7)
  - Sermon: Pres. Douglas M. Knight (Box 7)
- 1970
  - Programs (Box 7)
  - Address: Harold T. Parker (Box 7)
  - Student Address: Kenneth Vickery (Box 7)
- 1971
  - Programs (Box 7)
  - Address: Nancy Hanks (Box 7)
  - Sermon: Robert E. Cushman (Box 7)
  - Student Address: Byron R. Trauger (Box 7)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 7)
- 1972
  - Programs (Box 7)
  - Address: Walter Cronkite (Box 7)
  - Sermon: James T. Cleland (Box 7)
  - Student Address: Clarence G. Newsome (Box 7)
- 1973
  - Programs (Box 7)
  - Address: Vernon E. Jordan, The New South? (Box 7)
  - Sermon: Hugh Anderson (Box 7)
  - Student Address: Susan Tifft, A Rebirth of Individualism (Box 7)
- 1974
  - Programs (Box 7)
  - Address: Pierre Elliott Trudeau (P.M. Canada) (Box 7)
  - Sermon: Albert Outler (Box 7)
  - Student Address: John M. Robinson (Box 7)
- 1975
  - Programs (Box 7)
  - Remarks: Alexander Heard (Chancellor, Vanderbilt University) (Box 7)
- 1976
  - Programs (Box 8)
  - Address: Pres. Terry Sanford (Box 8)
  - Sermon: Donald W. Shrine (Box 8)
- 1977
  - Programs (Box 8)
  - Address: Juanita Kreps (Box 8)
  - Sermon: Arthur James Armstrong (Box 8)
  - Student Address: Ian Abrams (Box 8)
- 1978
  - Programs (Box 8)
  - Address: Glenn T. Seaborg (Box 8)
  - Sermons: Barney L. Jones and Gilleasbuig MacMillan (Box 8)
  - Student Address: Michelle Miller (Box 8)
  - Honorary Degree Citations (Box 8)
- 1979
  - Programs (Box 8)
  - Address: Pres. Terry Sanford (Box 8)
- 1980, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 8)
  - Sermon: Kenneth Goodson (Box 8)
  - Student Addresses: Hans Christian Linnartz and Judith Varner (Box 8)
  - Clippings (Box 8)
- 1981
  - Programs (Box 8)
  - Address: William Styron (Box 8)
  - Sermon: Peter Gomes (Box 8)
  - Student Addresses: Eugene Lavon Banks, Jr. and Harsha Murthy (Box 8)
- 1982, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 8)
  - Sermon: Dr. David H.C. Reed (Box 8)
  - Student Address: Frederick Robinson (Box 8)
  - Clippings and Misc. (Box 8)
- 1983, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 9)
  - Address: Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans (Box 9)
  - Student Address: Daniel S. Voll (Box 9)
  - Remarks: Barney L. Jones and William E. King (Box 9)
  - Clippings and Misc. (Box 9)
- 1984, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 9)
  - Address: Katharine Graham (Box 9)
  - Clippings articles and Misc. (Box 9)
- 1985, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 9)
  - Address: Rev. Theodore M. Hesburgh (Box 9)
  - Statement to Students: Pres. Terry Sanford, Doing Something about Apartheid (Box 9)
  - Clippings and Misc. (Box 9)
- 1986, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 9)
  - Address: Lee A. Iacocca (Box 9)
  - Student Address: David M. Allen (Box 9)
  - Remarks: Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans [Distinguished Alumni Award] (Box 9)
  - Clippings and misc. (Box 9)
- 1987, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 10)
  - Address: Ted Koppel (Box 10)
  - Student Address: Frederick W. Gissler, III (Box 10)
  - Clippings and misc. (Box 10)
- 1988, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 10)
  - Address: Garry Trudeau (Box 10)
  - Student Address: David Feitel (Box 10)
  - Clippings and misc. (Box 10)
- 1989, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 10)
  - Address: Stephen Jay Gould (Box 10)
  - Sermon: William H. Willimon (Box 10)
  - Clippings and misc. (Box 10)
- 1990, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 10)
  - Address: Tom Brokaw (Box 10)
  - Student Address: Meechelle Evans (Box 10)
  - Sermon: William H. Williamon (Box 10)
- 1991, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 11)
  - Address: George F. Will (Box 11)
  - Sermon: William H. Willimon (Box 11)
  - Fuqua School Address: Harold A. Poling (Ford Motor Company) (Box 11)
- 1992, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 11)
  - Address: Martin Wright Edelman (Box 11)
  - Sermon: William H. Willimon (Box 11)
  - Clippings and misc. (Box 11)
- 1993, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 11)
  - Address: Bill Bradley (Box 11)
  - Clippings and misc. (Box 11)
- 1994, 3 folders
  - Programs (Box 11)
  - Address: Judy Woodruff (Box 11)
  - Clippings and misc. (Box 11)
- 1995, 3 folders
  - Programs (Box 12)
  - Address: David Gergen (Box 12)
  - Baccalaureate Address: Nannerl O. Keohane (Box 12)
  - Clippings and misc. (Box 12)
- 1996, 2 folders
  - Programs (Box 12)
  - Address: Jane Alexander (Box 12)
  - Sermon: William H. Willimon (Box 12)
  - Charge to Class of '96: Pres. Nannerl O. Keohane (Box 12)
  - Divinity School Sermon: Richard Lischer (Box 12)
  - Clippings and misc. (Box 12)
- 1997, 5 folders
  - Programs (Box 12)
  - Clippings (Box 12)
  - Honorary Degrees (Box 12)
  - Charge to Class of '97: Pres. Nannerl O. Keohane (Box 12)
  - Divinity School Sermon: David Steinmetz (Box 12)
  - Address: Jimmy Carter
    - Notes and Correspondence (Box 12)
- 1998, 6 folders
  - Clippings (Box 13)
  - Baccalaureate Programs (Box 13)
  - Other programs (Box 13)
  - Charge to Class of '98: Pres. Nannerl O. Keohane (Box 13)
  - Baccalaureate Programs and Sermon: William H. Willimon (Box 13)
  - Student Address: Cristina Cardoze (Box 13)
  - Address: George W. Bush (Box 13)
- 1999, 6 folders
  - Clippings (Box 13)
  - Baccalaureate Programs (Box 13)
  - Other programs (Box 13)
  - Address: Cokie Roberts (Box 13)
  - Charge to Class of '99: Pres. Nannerl O. Keohane (Box 13)
  - Student Address: Samantha Wood (Box 13)
- 2000, 6 folders
  - Clippings (Box 13)
  - Baccalaureate Programs (Box 13)
  - Other programs (Box 13)
  - Address: Elizabeth Dole (Box 13)
  - Charge to Class of '00: Pres. Nannerl O. Keohane (Box 13)
  - Student Address, clippings (Box 13)
- 2001, 5 folders
  - Clippings (Box 14)
  - Baccalaureate programs (Box 14)
  - Other programs (Box 14)
  - Commencement programs (Box 14)
  - Charge to Class of '01: Pres. Nannerl O. Keohane (Box 14)
- 2002, 7 folders
  - Baccalaureate programs (Box 14)
  - Commencement programs (Box 14)
  - Address: Tom Wolfe (Box 14)
  - Clippings (Box 14)
  - Other graduation programs (Box 14)
  - Honorary Degrees (Box 14)
  - Other events (Box 14)
- 2003, 3 folders
  - Commencement programs (Box 14)
  - Divinity School programs (Box 14)
  - Other graduation programs (Box 14)
- 2004, 2 folders
  - Commencement programs (Box 14)
  - Other graduation programs (Box 14)
- 2005, 2 folders
  - Commencement programs (Box 14)
  - Other graduation programs (Box 14)
- 2005, 3 folders
  - Baccalaureate service, organ recital (Box 15)
  - Other graduation programs (Box 15)
  - Commencement exercises (Box 15)
- 2006, 4 folders
  - Address: John Hope Franklin (Box 15)
  - Commencement exercises (Box 15)
  - Baccalaureate service (Box 15)
  - Commencement program, Fuqua School of Business (Box 15)
- 2007, 3 folders
  - Baccalaureate service (Box 15)
  - Commencement exercises (Box 15)
  - Commencement program, Fuqua School of Business (Box 15)
- 2008, 5 folders
  - Baccalaureate service (Box 15)
  - Address: Barbara Kingsolver (Box 15)
  - Calendar of events (Box 15)
  - Commencement exercises (Box 15)
- 2009, 2 folders
  - Commencement exercises (Box 16)
  - Commencement exercises, Fuqua School of Business (Box 16)
- 2010, 2 folders
  - Commencement exercises (Box 16)
  - Commencement exercises, Fuqua School of Business (Box 16)
- 2011, 2 folders
  - Commencement exercises (Box 16)
  - Commencement exercises, Fuqua School of Business (Box 16)
- 2012
  - Commencement exercises (Box 16)
  - Commencement exercises, Fuqua School of Business (Box 16)
- 2013
  - Commencement exercises (Box 16)
  - Commencement exercises, Fuqua School of Businesss (Box 16)
- 2014
  - Commencement exercises (Box 16)
  - Commencement exercises, Fuqua School of Business (Box 16)
- 2015
  - Commencement exercises (Box 16)
  - Commencement exercises, Fuqua School of Business (Box 16)
- 2016
  - Commencement exercises (Box 18)
  - Commencement exercises, Fuqua School of Business (Box 18)
- 2017
  - Commencement exercises (Box 18)
  - Commencement exercises, Fuqua School of Business (Box 18)
  - Commencement exercises, Departmental (Box 18)
- 2018
  - Commencement exercises (Box 18)
  - Commencement exercises, Fuqua School of Business (Box 18)
- 2019
  - University Commencement Exercises, 2019 (Box 18)
- 2020-2021
  - Commencement exercises (Box 18)
- 2022
  - Commencement exercises, 2 folders (Box 18)
- 2023
  - Commencement exercises (Box 18)